Guide to the Alfred Austin Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alfred Austin collection
1865-1915
GEN MSS 219
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, writings and photographs by or about Alfred Austin. The correspondence consists of 14 letters from Austin to various people,and over 140 letters to Austin or his wife. The writings consist of holograph drafts, typescripts, and proofs of poems, playscripts, and notes by Austin. The photographs consist of portraits of Austin and views of his estate, Swinford.
Austin, Alfred, 1835-1913
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Alfred Austin.
Poets, English -- 19th century; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Playscripts; Austin, Alfred, 1835-1913
- Correspondence, Series I
  - LETTERS FROM ALFRED AUSTIN
    - ALS to Lawrence Curtis, Ashford, Kent, 1911 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to Mr. Dennis, Ashford, Kent, 1896 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS to Mrs. Dodd, Ashford, Kent, 1901 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Accompanied by a note, probably in the hand of Mrs. Austin.
    - ALS to Mrs. Edwards, [Hailey, Oxfordshire?], 1867 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS to Mrs. Frederick William Farrar, Florence, 1903 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ALS to Henry Jones, Ashford, Kent, 1893 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS to Mrs. Lowther, Ashford, Kent, 1900 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS to Theophilus Julius Henry Marzials, Ashford, Kent, 1889 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to Mr. Pennell, Ashford, Kent, 1869 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Mr. Robinson, Ashford, Kent, 1895 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Writes that the Poet Laureateship has just been offered to him.
    - ALS to Mrs. Woodruff, Ashford, Kent, 1907 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS to Mr. I. C. Wright, Ashford, Kent, 1896 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, Swinford Old Manor, Ashford, Kent, 1892 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Ashford, Kent, 1899 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Addressed to the Editor of The Independent, formerly The Nonconformist.
  - LETTERS TO ALFRED AUSTIN AND HIS WIFE
    - Ainley, Henry Hinchliffe, 1879-. 2 ALS to Alfred Austin regarding the possible production of A Successful Rehearsal and Achilles in Scyros, London, 1910 Feb 2, Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888. ALS to Alfred Austin, Cobham, Surrey, 1888 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Containing a criticism of Austin's Prince Lucifer.
    - Balfour, Arthur James, 1st earl, 1848-1930. 2 letters written by an amanuesis, signed by Mr. Balfour, London, 1896 Dec 2, 1897 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      The letters are addressed to Alfred Austin and are concerned with the granting of a pension to Mrs. Anthony Trollope.
    - Beresford, Charles William De la Poer Beresford, 1st baron, 1846-1919. ALS to Alfred Austin, London, 1898 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Blunt, Wilfrid Scawen, 1840-1922
      - ALS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, Southwater, Sussex, 1913 Jun 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - 8 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1897 Jun 21-1908 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bourget, Minnie Paul. ANS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, Le Plantier de Costebelle, 1909 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      The note concerns a postcard which she is returning to Mrs. Wharton.
    - Bourget, Paul Charles Joseph, 1852-1935
      - ANS to Alfred Austin, Golspie, Sutherland, 1892 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - ALS to Alfred Austin, Paris, 1906 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cambridge. University. Christ's college. Engraved invitation to Alfred Austin, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 22)
      From the Master and Fellows, to attend a dinner on July 10, 1908 celebrating the tercentenary of Milton.
    - Corry, Montagu William Lowry-, baron Rowton, 1838-1903
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Rowton, Montagu William Lowry-Corry, baron, 1838-1903, Box 1, folder 39
    - Dowden, Edward, 1843-1913. 13 ALS to Alfred Austin, Dublin, 1887-1910 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Hamilton, Lord George Francis, 1845-1927. ALS to Alfred Austin, London, 1878 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Harrison, Frederic, 1831-1923
      - 10 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1897 Oct 23-1911 [Jul?] 26 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - 5 ALS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1909 Aug 29-1913 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894. 3 ALS to Alfred Austin, Boston, 1891 Mar 7- May 30 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - James, Henry, 1843-1916. 4 ALS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1901-15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Lowry-Corry, Montagu William, baron Rowton, 1838-1903
    - Lytton, Edward George Earle Lytton Bulwer-Lytton, 1st baron, 1803-1873. ANS to Alfred Austin inviting him to lunch with Charles Dickens and others, Knebworth, 1865 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st earl of, 1831-1891
      - 25 ALS to Alfred Austin, [n.p.], 1873-91 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
      - 13 ALS to Alfred Austin, selected by himself for his autobiography, [n.p.], 1881-88 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
    - Mallock, William Hurrell, 1849-1923. 9 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1886-1910 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Master, J. ANS to Alfred Austin, [London], 1895 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Maxse, Frederick Augustus, 1833-1900. 4 ALS to Alfred Austin, 1891-98, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34a)
      With 2 envelopes.
    - Meredith, George, 1828-1909. 8 ALS to Alfred Austin, [London], 1891 Dec 8-1903 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      With 7 envelopes. The letters contain comments on Austin's poems.
    - Morley, John Morley, viscount, 1838-1923. 4 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1879 May 2-1905 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Nordau, Max Simon, 1849-
      - 10 ALS to Alfred Austin, Paris, 1897 Jul 2-1908 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - ALS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, Paris, 1913 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Patmore, Coventry Kersey Dighton, 1823-1896. ALS to Alfred Austin, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Thanking him for his favorable criticism, and discussing the use of a certain metre in poetry.
    - Rowton, Montagu William Lowry-Corry, baron, 1838-1903. 2 ALS to Alfred Austin, London, 1895 Apr 11-1896 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Sharp, William, 1855-1905. 5 ALS to Alfred, Austin, [v.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Smith, William Henry, 1825-1891. 4 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1886 Jan 13-1889 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Ward, Mary Augusta Arnold, 1851-1920
      - 2 ALS to Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1887 Jan 31-1895 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - 3 ALS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, [v.p.], 1887-89, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Wood, Sir Evelyn, i.e. Henry Evelyn, 1838-1919. TLS to Mrs. Alfred Austin, London, 1897 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Writings, Series II
  - "Achilles in Scyros"
    - 2 typescripts, one with holograph corrections, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Page proofs, with holograph corrections and additions, 1910 Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
  - Progamme of Pastoral plays at Leighton House, where on Monday, July 19th, 1909 this masque was given (Box 2, Folder 48)
    A clipping from The Times, July 20, 1909 is laid in. Also laid in is the estimate from Macmillan & Co. for printing this work together with sample pages; and a memorandum from R & R Clark, ltd., of Edinburgh submitting fresh proof of title-sheet.
  - "After Leonidas," autograph poem, 16 lines (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Printed on p. 20 of Lamia's Winter Quarters, London 1898.
  - "Birthday Book," autograph [?] manuscript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
    A work similar to "Days of the Year." On wrapping: "The H. L.'s Birthday Book (MS)."
  - "A Border Burn," autograph draft of the poem printed in his A Tale of True Love, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "Cassandra Speaks," autograph, with typescript, corrected (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Autograph endorsed: "not needed;" typescript endorsed: "To be returned to me, when used for the purpose now sent. AA."
  - "The Converson of Winckelmann," autograph draft of part of the poem, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Over the next to last page are approximately 4 stanzas of "John Everett Millais," a poem printed in the same volume. Laid in a folder marked "Winckelmann Right (?) Draft."
  - "The Dance at Treves," autograph manuscript, signed, with corrections and additions (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "Dante's Poetic Conception of Woman," typescripts, with holograph corrections, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - "Dante's Realistic Treatment of the Ideal," autograph and typescript, corrected (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
  - "The Door of Humility," autograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60-61)
  - "England's Darling," autograph manuscript with title, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "England's Darling," autograph draft of the preface (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - "The Essentials of Great Poetry," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - "Flodden Field"
    - Page proof, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "The original draft of Flodden Field: written in April 1901, at the Villa Favorita, Florence." (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "A Florilegium," autograph draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
    Printed in "The Conversion of Winckelmann."
  - "Forget and Forgive," autograph and typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - "The Garden That I Love," autograph of missing chapters in "The Garden That I Love", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - "In The Forum," autograph draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
    Later revised and printed in A Tale of True Love.
  - "Lamia's Meditations," and "What Do We Know of Shakespeare?," autograph manuscript (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - "Madonna's Child," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - "The Mercy of the Mighty," autograph manuscript of a poem published in Songs of England, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    With another autograph manuscript of a draft of the above poem.
  - Poems, autographs of "poems not published or for later consideration", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - "Poems &c published - AA," autograph manuscripts, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Poems, clippings, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    One poem, "The Evening Light," has corrections in Austin's hand.
  - "The Poet's Diary," autograph manuscript, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    Includes the following note in Austin's hand: "Rejected by me from the MS of "The Poet's Diary," but proving useful elsewhere. April 3, 1904. Some of it perhaps to be used in the Diary. (see leaf 6 &c)."
  - "Polyphemus," autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 78)
    Printed in his A Tale of True Love, New York & London, 1902, p. 65-81.
  - "Power," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    Caption on the first leaf reads: "For "Power" Progress." (The word Power is crossed through in pencil).
  - "Progess, A Comedy," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - "Quotations and References" (Box 3, Folder 81)
    A folder so marked by Austin, containing clippings from various newspapers.
  - "Savonarola," page proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82-85)
    Brown paper wrappers. On cover of volume I: "Stratford-upon-Avon Prize Play Competition. Competitor No. 135."
  - "Sonnets and Lyrics unpublished and not yet written out 1908," autograph manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - "A Successful Rehearsal," typescript, with autograph corrections, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
    Laid in the manuscript are two letters from the International copyright bureau ltd., Oct 31, 1910, Sep 1912, regarding the placing of the play. On verso of first letter is a draft in pencil, signed, of Austin's reply.
  - "The Tenant of Avoncourt," typescript, with autograph corrections and additions, 3 parts (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - "To a Poet," 2 typescripts, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - "To Robert Louis Stevenson," autograph of the sonnet published in Austin's A Tale of True Love, New York & London, 1902, p. xiii-xiv (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - "Victoria," autograph manuscript, 1837-97 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    Jubilee ode printed in 1897.
  - "Victoria! Victoria!," autograph of poem of three stanzas, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - "What Do We Know of Shakespeare"
    See: "Lamia's Meditations," Box 3, folder 71
  - "What is Philosophy?," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 93)
    Inaugural address delivered to the Edinburgh philosophical institution at the opening of its winter session.
  - "What is Progress," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Pass to the House of Lords, endorsed by Lord Salisbury, with Austin's signature, 1893 Sep 8 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    Accompanied by two photographs of Austin.
- Photographs, n.d.; Series III
  - Portrait proof by S. Hollyer, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - 2 photographs of his estate, Swinford Old Manor, Kent, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - 2 photographs of Austin
    See: Pass to the House of Lords, Box 3, folder 95
- Additions Since July 1998, Series IV
  - LETTERS FROM ALFRED AUSTIN
    - ALS to Dr. Maurice Ernest, Swinford Old Manor, Kent, 1905 Dec 15 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - ALS to Mackenzie Bell, Swinford Old Manor, Kent, [1899?] Nov 2 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - LETTER TO ALFRED AUSTIN
    - Stephen, Leslie, Sir, 1832-1904 (Box 4, Folder 100)
      - ALS to Alfred Austin., [18]79 May 7
      - With: Holograph draft of reply by Austin to Stephen on verso